Guide to the May Chen Papers WAG.301
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
May Chen Papers
1980-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Chen, May Ying
WAG.301
17.75 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes,1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box, 1 artifact box, 1 cassette box, and 2 oversize folders.
28 Gigabytes on 5 CD-R, 3 CD-RW, and 6 DVD-R
3 videodiscs (dvd)
6 videocassettes (vhs)
4 videocassettes (minidv)
13 videocassettes (vhs-c)
1 audiocassette
May Chen (1948- ) is a labor organizer who has been actively engaged in outreach and advocacy for immigrant workers for over 20 years. Most of the files in her collection relate to May Chen's work as a labor organizer and community activist in the New York's Chinatown from 1989 to 2015. The first component is organizing Chinese immigrant garment workers to fight sweatshop conditions. These files contain newspaper clippings, logistic planning documents, meeting notes, contact lists, press releases, flyers and memos for UNITE's Chinatown Rally to Stop Sweatshops on August 28, 1998. The other component of Chen's collection consists of advocacy work to aid Chinatown's economic recovery after 9/11.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
May Chen sent a gift of 7 boxes of her papers in 2009. The accession number associated with this gift is 2009.004. Chen sent an additional 3 boxes of papers relating to her work with the clothing industry in 2010. The accession number associated with this gift is 2010.091. In 2012, Tamiment received a donation of papers related to May Chen and Rocky Chin. One box of materials from this donation pertaining to May Chen were added to this collection. The accession number associated with these materials is 2012.008. May Chen donated an additional 11 boxes of her papers in 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.078.
Historical/Biographical Note
May Chen (1948- ) is a labor organizer who has been actively engaged in outreach and advocacy for immigrant workers for over 20 years. Born and raised in Boston, MA, she worked as a high school teacher, wrote for the Asian-American publications Gidra and Roots, founded a day-care center that employed mainly immigrant women, and served as a local officer (Local 23-25) and International Vice President of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union (later UNITE, UNITE/HERE, and Workers United).
Other Finding Aids
A preliminary inventory of the first five boxes is available on request.
Related Archival Materials
The papers of May Chen's husband, Rockwell "Rocky" Chin, are also located at this repository. See the Rocky Chin Papers (WAG 325).
Scope and Content Note
Most of the files in this collection relate to two components of May Chen's work as a labor organizer and community activist in the New York's Chinatown from 1989 to 2005. The first component is organizing Chinese immigrant garment workers to fight sweatshop conditions. These files contain newspaper clippings, logistic planning documents, meeting notes, contact lists, press releases, flyers and memos for UNITE's Chinatown Rally to Stop Sweatshops on August 28, 1998. The other component of Chen's collection consists of advocacy work to aid Chinatown's economic recovery after 9/11. These files include reports and conference materials relating to a variety of organizations, for example, Asian Americans for Equality's Rebuild Chinatown Initiative, the Asian American Federation's economic impact study of Chinatown after Sept 11th, and the Asian American Leadership Conference, "Healing and Rebuilding in New York," held on May 10, 2002. In addition, there are materials relating to Chen's work as a founding member and executive officer of the Asian-Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA); these include a constitution and chapter by-laws, an application for tax exempt status, contact mailing lists, an executive board directory, and a directory of Asian-American organizations in New York and California.
Materials added to the collection in 2018 consist primarily of training guides, pamphlets, and reports on Asian American labor rights and labor organizing. They largely focus on Asian American workers in the garment industry and workers in New York City's Chinatown including the work of organizations like the APALA; the Service Employees International Union (SEIU), Local 1199; and the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees and Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union (UNITE/HERE) between the 1990s and early 2000s. The accretion also contains several travel journals and labor tour journals May Chen kept during trips to China and Japan between 1999 and 2011. Other materials include photo albums from Chen's travels and work in labor organizing, as well as collected memorabilia such as buttons, conference badges, collected movies on VHS, and posters. Several original video recordings also feature footage of speeches, demonstrations, and conferences between 1988 and 2005, including footage of Jesse Jackson speaking in Chinatown in 1988 and footage from May Chen's travels to China and South East Asia.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Textile workers -- Labor unions -- 20th century; Asian Americans -- Economic conditions.; Asian Americans -- Social conditions.; Women labor leaders.; Minority labor union members.; Chen, May Ying
- Spanish, English and Chinese Posters, Newsletters and Pamphlets on Immigration Rights and Activism 2002-2007, 487339 (Box 1)
  - Posters of Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride (in English and Spanish), 2003; 487340 (Box 1)
  - Unite! Poster in Spanish, 2003; 487341 (Box 1)
  - Unite! Shopping Guide Brochure-Made in New York, 2003; 487342 (Box 1)
  - Unite! Local 23-25 Newsletters in English, Spanish and Chinese, 2003; 487343 (Box 1)
  - Unite! Voice from Knitgoods Workers' Union, Local 155, Autumn 2002; 487344 (Box 1)
  - Unite! New York Metropolitan Area Joint Board News in English, Spanish and Chinese, 2007; 487345 (Box 1)
- Unite! and Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance materials; various other bulletins, reports and files relating to immigration activism 1991-2004, 487346 (Box 2)
  - Unite! Bookmarks: Proudly made in New York, 487347 (Box 2)
  - Slogan Stickers: Save America, Defeat Bush; Wal-Mart Sucks, 487348 (Box 2)
  - Postcards: What Part of Union Made Don't You Understand?, 487349 (Box 2)
  - Group Photo of Local 23-25, 487350 (Box 2)
  - Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance Brochures in English, Chinese, Korean, Vietnamese and Filipino, 487351 (Box 2)
  - 2 Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance Binders from Executive Board Meetings January 13-14, 2001 in Greensboro, North Carolina and August 11-13, 2000 in New York, New York, January 2001; 487352 (Box 2)
  - Vote 2000 Program Binder from Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance and American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations Political Education Conference in Los Angeles February 18-20, 2000, February 2000; 487353 (Box 2)
    - Get Out the Vote Program Workshop Manual, 487354 (Box 2)
  - Unite Here! Activist Pins, 2004; 487355 (Box 2)
  - Lower Manhattan Development Corporation World Trade Center Memorial and Redevelopment Plan: Environmental Assessment for Proposed Refinements to Approved Plan, April 2005, 487356 (Box 2)
  - Unite! National Retirement Fund Pamphlet, 487357 (Box 2)
  - Resource Files, 1999; 487358 (Box 2)
    - Legal Advice 1999, 487359 (Box 2)
    - Recession and September 11th; 2003, 487360 (Box 2)
    - Economic statistics of Asian Pacific Americans, 1988, 487361 (Box 2)
    - Asian American Women, 2002, 487362 (Box 2)
    - Chinese immigration and Chinese in the United States: Records in the Regional Archives, 1996, 487363 (Box 2)
    - Lessons Learned from a Program to Sustain Health Coverage after September 11th in New York City's Chinatown, by Asian American Federation New York, 2004, 487364 (Box 2)
    - IKON 9: Without Ceremony, by Australian Workers Union featuring writings by May Chen, 1998, 487365 (Box 2)
    - Many Paths, One Goal: Organizing Women Workers in Asia, by Committee for Asian Women, 1991, 487366 (Box 2)
    - Asian American Elders in New York City: A Study of Health, Social Needs, Quality of Life and Quality of Care, by Asian American Federation New York, 2003, 487367 (Box 2)
  - Unite! Directories; Fall/Winter 2001; Spring 2004, 487368 (Box 2)
  - 1998-2001 Survey: Critique of Trade Union Rights in Countries Affiliated with the League of Arab States, by Jewish Labor Committee; 2003, 487369 (Box 2)
  - The Workers United Will Never Be Defeated in English, Japanese, and Chinese; 2002, 487370 (Box 2)
  - Summary Report: Asian Pacific Islander Workers Hearing, by Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance and University of California Los Angeles Labor Center; 2002, 487371 (Box 2)
  - A Tenement Story, by Lower East Side Tenement Museum; 2004, 487372 (Box 2)
  - Bulletin: Center for Transnational Labor Studies; December 1999, February 2001, April 2002, 487373 (Box 2)
  - Japan Labor Review, by Japan Institute for Labor Policy and Training; Spring 2004, 487374 (Box 2)
  - National Union Voice, by National Union of General Workers in English and Japanese; August 2003, 487375 (Box 2)
  - List of Japanese union representatives attending Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance Convention, 487376 (Box 2)
  - Rebuild Chinatown Initiative: The Community Speaks One Year After September 11, 2001, convened by Asian Americans for Equality; November 2002, 487377 (Box 2)
  - Interim Report: Chinatown After September 11th: An Economic Impact Study, by Asian American Federation New York; April 2002, 487378 (Box 2)
  - Binder from Workers' Center-aimed at organizing non-union Chinese garment workers in Sunset Park, 487379 (Box 2)
  - Hanging files-business agents shop, Richard Guido and Joseph Delli Carpini, 487381 (Box 2)
  - Unite! price guide and piece guide book, 487382 (Box 2)
  - Materials obtained through Freedom of Information and Privacy Act re: International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 487383 (Box 2)
  - Immigrant Freedom Ride Files, some in Haitian, Chinese, and French, 2003; 487384 (Box 2)
  - Unite! Immigration Project Files, 1999; 487385 (Box 2)
  - Program from New York City Central Labor Council Annual Dinner Dance and Awards Ceremony, 487386 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets: China AIDS Fund and National Coalition for Haitian Rights, 487387 (Box 2)
  - Group photo, 1999 Unite! Convention – Local 23-25 Delegation, 487388 (Box 2)
- Unite! files, Local 23-25 materials, newspaper clippings, and Asian American Leadership Conference, 2000; 487389 (Box 3)
  - Tenement Museum Lower East Side Fabric of Our Communities Program, "Garment Industry Present", 487390 (Box 3)
  - UNITE Education Deptartment 2000 file, 487391 (Box 3)
  - Resolution Number 1083 calling upon Governor Pataki and New York State Department of Labor to keep open unemployment telephone claims center in lower Manhattan, 487392 (Box 3)
  - May Chen's testimony, correspondence, clipping from Chinese-language newspapers for hearing re: unemployment; July 8, 2005, 487393 (Box 3)
  - UNITE HERE! for Bloomberg flyers and Chinese-language newspaper clips, 487394 (Box 3)
  - Sweatshops information file-clippings, articles, Unite! briefing sheet, Anti-sweatshop Procurement Bille, Petition to President, 487395 (Box 3)
  - New York City Apparel Industry Compliance Program, 487396 (Box 3)
  - News clippings in Chinese from Sing Tao Daily; 2000, 487397 (Box 3)
  - UNITE information material re: Stop Sweatshops Act, S 626, HR 23, in Chinese and English, 487398 (Box 3)
  - Anti-sweatshops material, support Chinatown garment workers material, draft statement of support from New York chapter of Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance, 487399 (Box 3)
  - Local 23-25 rally/lobby in Washington D.C.; July 29, 1998, 487400 (Box 3)
  - Local 23-25 textbook scholarship award ceremony; 2000, 2003, 487401 (Box 3)
  - Packet given to Deputy Mayor Dennis Walcott re: September 11th and recovery and Rebuild Chinatown Initiative, by Asian Americans for Equality and Asian American Federation New York; March 2002, 487402 (Box 3)
  - Asian American Leadership Conference: Healing and Rebuilding New York; May 10, 2002, 487403 (Box 3)
  - Chinese press clippings-UNITE and workers; 2002-2003, 487404 (Box 3)
- Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance meeting materials and newsletters, American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations conference materials, New York City Central Labor Council materials, 2008; 487405 (Box 4)
  - Chinese language newspaper re: Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance, 487406 (Box 4)
  - Women's Apparel "Made in New York" Promotion Tour to promote to markets in China and Hong Kong; 1998, 487407 (Box 4)
  - Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance materials-constitution, application for tax exemption, executive board directory, membership renewal forms,mailing lists, Executive Board Meeting materials 2004-2008, Newsletter Winter 2005, 487408 (Box 4)
  - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations Civil Rights Conference, Baton Rouge; January 12-16, 2006, 487409 (Box 4)
  - Urban Agenda: Promoting an Equitable and Sustainable Economy, project of New York City Central Labor Council; 2006, 487410 (Box 4)
  - New York Industrial Retention Network's "Wake Up and Taste the City" Network Breakfast; 2003, 487411 (Box 4)
  - Drum Major Institute for Public Policy – prepares progressive college students from underrepresented communities for entry-level positions in public policy, 2006; 487412 (Box 4)
  - Cornell University School of Industrial and Labor Relations Union Leadersip Workshop; April/May 2007, 487413 (Box 4)
  - Consortium for Worker Education – service arm of the New York City Central Labor Council, 487414 (Box 4)
  - Chinatown Rally to Stop Sweatshops; August 28, 1998, 487415 (Box 4)
- Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act, "Research Papers," Vassar workshop, various conference materials, Coalition on Labor Union Women Asian-Chinese Committee, Unite! Chinatown Pre-retirement seminar, Doris-Ling-Cohan information; 1989-2000, 1996; 487419 (Box 5)
  - Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996, related materials file, 487423 (Box 5)
  - "Research Papers", 487424 (Box 5)
  - Vassar workshop on East Asian immigrant women: "The Other Half of the 'Model Minority'"; March 14-15, 1998, 487425 (Box 5)
  - Ford Foundation's "Asian American Women: Issues, Concerns and Responsive Human Rights and Civil Rights Advocacy" by Lora Jo Foo, 487426 (Box 5)
  - Testimony for public hearing sponsored by the White House Initiative on Asian Americans and Pacific Islanders; September 2000, 487427 (Box 5)
  - Cornell University "Organizing Immigrant Workers Conference; December 1, 1989, 487428 (Box 5)
  - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Resolution on China re: Tiananmen Square; June 1989, 487429 (Box 5)
  - Coalition on Labor Union Women Asian-Chinese Committee; 1993-1995, 487430 (Box 5)
  - UNITE Chinatown pre-retirement seminar; October 1997, 487431 (Box 5)
  - Doris Ling-Cohan for Civil Court Judge of Lower East Side; June 1992, 487432 (Box 5)
- Various reports, materials, and brochures. Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance Executive Board Meeting and convention materials 2007, New York Industrial Retention Network Manufacturer's Almanac 2007, Reference Guide to the Overseas Chinese History, book in Chinese, etc., 1999; 487433 (Box 7)
  - Women's Apparel Task Forse Meeting Materials; July 14, 1999, 487434 (Box 7)
  - Typed essay mailed to May Chen; April 1993, 487435 (Box 7)
  - Asian American Access to Democracy in 2008 Election, 487436 (Box 7)
  - 1199 Service Employee's International Union News; April 2002, 487437 (Box 7)
  - "Garment Industry Development Corporation-Ron Karpman Reports" 2003, 487438 (Box 7)
  - Profile of Chinese Community in New York, 487439 (Box 7)
  - New York City's Chinatown Garment Industry: A Critical Case of Ethnic Enterprise and Worker Organization, by Esther Song; May 1995, 487440 (Box 7)
  - Asian Pacific American Heritage Festival Brochure; May 8, 1993, 487441 (Box 7)
  - Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance "old files" 2003, 487442 (Box 7)
  - Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance Chapter Membership Report; February 3, 2000, 487443 (Box 7)
  - Chinatown Labor Fair Materials 1993, 487444 (Box 7)
  - Subsidizing Sweatshops Brochure; July 2008, 487445 (Box 7)
  - Apparel Industry Task Force 2005, 487446 (Box 7)
  - New York Industrial Retention Network Breakfast Materials; April 10, 2003, 487447 (Box 7)
  - Center for Working Families-Policies and Priorities for Working Families; December 7, 2007, 487448 (Box 7)
  - Apparel Industry Task Force Garment Manufacturers and Contractors Registration Database 1999, 487449 (Box 7)
  - "Earthquake" 2008, 487450 (Box 7)
  - Jing Fong 1995, 487451 (Box 7)
  - Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association of New York 120th Anniversary Edition in Chinese, 487452 (Box 7)
  - Asian Americans and Pacific Islanders Interim Report to the President and to the Nation; January 2001, 487453 (Box 7)
  - Eastward International Inc.-textile swatches, copies of checks, invoices etc. 2005, 487454 (Box 7)
  - Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance National Executive Board Meeting Folder; March 1-4, 2007, 487455 (Box 7)
  - Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance Executive Board Meeting Folder; July 19, 2007, 487456 (Box 7)
  - Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance 2007 Convention Materials, 487457 (Box 7)
  - Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance 10th Biennial Convention Brochure; July 9-12, 2009, 487458 (Box 7)
  - Asian Pacific Islanders Caucus Bylaws 1995-2008, 487459 (Box 7)
  - Moving On: chinese Garment Workers After September 11th; January 15, 2003, 487460 (Box 7)
  - New York Industrial Retention Network Manufacturer's Almanac 2007, 487461 (Box 7)
  - A Reference Guide to the Overseas Chinese History, book in Chinese, 487462 (Box 7)
- Business meeting minutes, City University of New York information, Lower Manhattan Development Plan Information, Asian American Federation of New York Research, etc., 2001-2008; 487467 (Box 8)
  - Chinatown/Lower East Side Empire Zone Administrative Board Meeting, June 29, 2007, 487468 (Box 8)
  - Chinatown/Lower East Side Empire Zone Administrative Meeting, December 8, 2006, 487469 (Box 8)
  - Hotel Committee Meeting, July 31, 2008, 487470 (Box 8)
  - Chinatown/Lower East Side Empire Zone Administrative Board Meeting, October 19, 2007, 487471 (Box 8)
  - Minutes from Chinatown/Lower East Side Empire Zone Administrative Board Meeting, October 19, 2007, 487472 (Box 8)
  - Empire Zone (2 folders)-Minutes from October 19, 2007, Zone Development Plan, Zone Capital Credits, Agenda from Department of Small Business Services Meeting, March 23, 2007, Empire Zone Application July 15, 2002, Press Release June 12, 2002, etc., 487473 (Box 8)
  - East River Science Park Empire Zone, Proposal to re-draw Chinatown/Lower East Side Empire Zone, September 26, 2008, 487474 (Box 8)
    - Application for Joint Certification of an Empire Zone Business Enterprise, 487475 (Box 8)
  - Hotel Committee Meeting September 10, 2008, 487476 (Box 8)
  - City University of New York information-Graduate Admissions Guide, Opportunities for Adults, Faculty List, 2001, 487477 (Box 8)
  - Unemployment Insurance Issues 2001, 487478 (Box 8)
  - Asian American Federation of New York Research 2002, 487479 (Box 8)
  - Women's Apparel Industrial Task Force 2000, 487480 (Box 8)
  - Consortium for Worker Education 2002, 487481 (Box 8)
  - Health Partnership, September 11th Chinatown Rebuild Program 2002, 487482 (Box 8)
  - "Jobs Now-Unemployed Workers Campaign" 2001, 487483 (Box 8)
  - Grant Proposal September 11th Fund, Lower Manhattan Development Corporation 2001-2002, 487484 (Box 8)
  - Lower Manhattan Development 2004, 487485 (Box 8)
  - Event Flyers 2001-2002, 487486 (Box 8)
  - Job Training Classes 2002, 487487 (Box 8)
  - Statements and Testimonies 2002, 487488 (Box 8)
  - Research Papers Post September 11th Reports 2002, 487489 (Box 8)
  - Garment Industry Development Corporation and Local 23-25 Documents 2001-2002, 487490 (Box 8)
- Garment Industry Devlopment Corporation Reports, Chinese and English Newspapers, September 11th training, Report to Congress etc., 2004; 487624 (Box 9)
  - Asian American Federation of New York 2004-2005, 487625 (Box 9)
  - Sectoral Employment Development Learning Project, The Garment Industry Development Corporation, November 1999, 487626 (Box 9)
  - Garment Industry Development Corporation Annual Report, 2001-2002, 487627 (Box 9)
  - September 11th-Chinese newspaper clippings, address list, and letters 2003, 487628 (Box 9)
  - Fiscal Policy Institute, New York City's Garment Industry, A New Look? Report by Sarah Crean, August 2003, 487629 (Box 9)
  - Garment Industry Development Corporation Sourcing Project 1998-1999, 487630 (Box 9)
  - Garment Center Zoning 2003-2007, 487631 (Box 9)
  - Clean Clothes Campaign Poster, Stitched Up by the Big Brands, 2000, 487632 (Box 9)
  - Project on Independent Verification of Compliance with Code of Conduct in Garment Industry, (English and German), 487633 (Box 9)
  - Garment Workers Voice Newsletter, 487634 (Box 9)
  - The Wall Street Journal September 6, 2002, 487635 (Box 9)
  - Forms-Job Training Questionnaire for Unite Members (English and Chinese), 487636 (Box 9)
  - 2002 Applications for September 11th Apparel Bidders Registry Respondents, 487637 (Box 9)
  - September 11th Bidders Registry Mailing List August 2002, 487638 (Box 9)
  - Apparel 2003, 487639 (Box 9)
  - The Chinatown Garment Industry Study June 1983 by Local 23-25, International Ladies' Garment Workers Union and New York Skirt and Sportswear Association, 487640 (Box 9)
  - Industry 1998-1999, 487641 (Box 9)
  - Report to Congress of the United States-China Economic and Security Review Commission June 2004, 487642 (Box 9)
  - Local 23-25 Folder 2001-2003, 487643 (Box 9)
  - Zoning-Garment Center 2003-2007, 487644 (Box 9)
  - September 11th Training 2003, 487645 (Box 9)
  - Fashion Bid Report 2002, 487646 (Box 9)
  - Women's Wear Daily Newspaper July 29, 2003, 487647 (Box 9)
  - New York City Industrial Policy, Projecting and Growing New York City's Industrial Job Base, January 2005, 487648 (Box 9)
  - Women's Wear Daily July 21 to July 22, 2003, July 21-July 23, 2003; 487649 (Box 9)
  - Calendar of Public Hearings on Contract Awards September 4, 2003, 487650 (Box 9)
  - Various Chinese Newspaper Clippings 2001, 487651 (Box 9)
  - Garment Industry Development Corporation-Made in New York 2002-2003, 487652 (Box 9)
  - Chinese Press Releases 2001-2002, 487653 (Box 9)
- East Coast Asian Student Union Conferences, National Conference on Women and the Law, Memorial Notebook for Professor Lee C. Lee, Po Ling Ng's School Board Election etc. 1960-2006, 1960s-2002; 452460 (Box 10)
  - East Coast Asian Student Union 2002 Workshop Leader, Sweatshops and Labor, 487654 (Box 10)
  - Asian Women: Myth and Reality, East Coast Asian Student Union at Mt. Holyoke, March 6-March 7, 1981, 487655 (Box 10)
  - May Ying Chen-Event Location Guide, 16th National Conference on Women and the Law, letter from Lesbian Caucus 1985, 487656 (Box 10)
  - Women and the Law Conference 1984, 487657 (Box 10)